Hussain Mahfood Al-Kamel

Personal Information

- Nationality: Bahraini
- Contact Number: +973 36300222
- Email: hussain@mahfood.ws

Summary

Technical Leader with more than 25 years of experience working in technology in a variety of industries, including financial, retail, and logistics sectors, as well as government and semi-government. Convert difficult projects, particularly those involving software and hardware, into successful deliveries at local and regional locations.

Experience

Freelancer (2022 to Present)

- Lead ERP Implementations
- Build Cloud Systems (Private/Public/Hybrid/SaaS) with Amazon Web Service and Microsoft Azure and Office 365
- Development Web and Mobile Applications
- Develop Effective Business Intelligent Analytics and Insights
- Provide Artificial Intelligent / Deep Learning Solutions and Trainings

Board Member: Academic-Industry Advisory Board (AIAB)- Master of Science – Artificial Intelligence at Bahrain Polytechnic

<u>Projects Completed</u>: GrandMark, Daaem, Masdar, Dar AlBayan, BahrainPets, AdCharge, Saeed AlSamak, Pioneers Professional Sports Training Services, Al Qassab Automatic Doors, Bahrain Pearls Kindergarten, ThinkSmart, Arabian Gulf University, Excel Accountancy, Al Fares Motors, Saar Service Station

Head of PMO & Business Applications – International Payment Services (June 2023 to August 2023)

- Manage the delivery of Five Projects across Four Clients engagements
- Lead ERP Implementation
- Collaborated with IT to resolve security vulnerabilities identified through penetration testing
- Evaluated strategic IT options for on-premises, cloud, and SaaS deployments
- Served as interim Business Development Representative

Senior Manager IT & I4.0 - BFG International (2017 to 2022)

- Lead Industry 4.0 Project
- Build new infrastructure with security, reliability, and availability (Microsoft, Cisco, VMware & Ruckus)
- Implement a new ERP system (Epicor)
- Used Artificial Intelligent in Planning with a Deep learning (Azure, AWS and Python)
- Evaluate Indoor Positioning and Tracking systems (UWB, Bluetooth and RFID)
- Industrial Internet of Things (IIOT) (Sensors, Custom Electronics Boards & handheld devices
- Augmented/Assisted Reality Solution (Microsoft Hololens)
- Autonomous machines (CNC and KUKA Robotics)
- Visualization and Dashboard (PowerBI and Custom Web Application)

Al Optimization Project Management between QiO and Sulb

IT Senior Executive - Economic Development Board (2005 to 2017)

- Managed and led IT teams.
- Managed IT system implementations and upgrades, including a full infrastructure relocation with only four hours of downtime.
- Developed technical standards and procedural documentation for system design, maintenance, and operation.
- Developed cost estimates for hardware and software procurements.
- Planned, tested, recommended, and implemented server, network, workstation, and storage hardware and software.
- Provided expert technical support, troubleshooting complex system problems and working with vendors to implement solutions.
- Consulted with users to gather requirements, recommend designs, provide cost analyses, and manage project implementation.
- Conducted feasibility studies to improve data center efficiency and effectiveness.

IT Consultant and Project Manager (as secondment) - Ministry of Finance (Aug 2010 to Dec 2010)

- Enhanced the Bahrain government's financial licensing system (Oracle E-Business Suite).
- Implemented disaster recovery solutions.
- Implemented and maintained ISO 27001 information security standards.
- Aligned IT strategy with e-Government strategy.
- Managed upgrades to core IT systems, including email, databases, websites (intranet and internet), firewalls, and server virtualization.
- Restructured the data center for environmental efficiency.
- Introduced cloud computing services using Azure and AWS.

Network Implementation Administrator – PWCLogistics (Agility) (2003 to 2005)

- Implemented IT systems across five Middle Eastern countries (Bahrain, Kuwait, Qatar, Saudi Arabia, and Jordan).
- Deployed and maintained Microsoft infrastructure including Active Directory, Windows Server, Exchange, SQL Server, SharePoint, and IIS.
- Managed IT asset, backup, and antivirus systems.
- Implemented and supported a helpdesk system for user support and business application assistance.
- Configured and maintained Cisco network infrastructure, including firewalls, routers, switches, and wireless systems.
- Established VoIP systems for international calls and VPN servers for secure remote access.
- Installed and configured hardware, software, UPS systems, and time attendance systems, including maintaining a Samsung PABX with call monitoring.

Network Support Engineer - Arab Financial Services (AFS) (1999 to 2003)

- Provided on-site and remote support to banks.
- Installed and administered diverse server infrastructure, including Exchange, proxy, SNA, backup, domain, DNS, RAS servers, and security software on Windows, Linux, and Unix platforms.
- Installed and configured Checkpoint firewalls.
- Supported client PCs running various operating systems (Windows 9x, NT4, 2000, XP, Linux, and Unix).

- Installed and maintained hardware and software, including WAN infrastructure (routers, leased lines, and connections to financial networks).
- Developed applications using Visual Basic, HTML, and Crystal Reports, and published websites.
- Connected mainframe systems (Z/OS and VSE/ESA) to LAN via Ethernet and Token Ring, and supported related hardware and CICS Cobol applications.
- Migrated legacy IBM routing systems to Cisco routers.
- Managed controllers, coax connections, and PC board emulators.
- Operated credit card embossing equipment.

IT Technician and Sales (Part-time) - (Delmon Information Technology, Virtual Technologies and SAMA Al-Computer) (1995 to 1999)

- Assembled and repaired personal computers.
- Configured routers and modems.
- Installed and configured servers.
- Installed software applications.

Education & Trainings

2023 - Thomson Reuters

- Financial Crime (Middle East)
- Operational Risk Management Essentials

2023 (12 Weeks Bootcamp) - General Assembly

- Software Engineering Immersive
 - Languages (Python, JavaScript)
 - Backend Systems (NodeJS, Express, Django)
 - Frontend Systems (React, Flutter, Bootstrap, jQuery, Ajax, Axios API, HTML, CSS)
 - Databases (SQL and NoSQL)
 - Operating Systems (Shell Scripting in Linux, Mac and Windows)
 - o Tools (GitHub version control, Microsoft Visual Studio IDE)

2018 - Amazon - BIBF Bahrain

AWS Systems Operations

2016 - Microsoft - ART Rotana

Azure IT Camp (Solutions Architect)

2016 - VMware

NSX vSphere: Install, Configure, Manage V5

Knowledge Village – Dubai, United Arab Emirates

2016 - BIBF

Effective Business Correspondence

2015 - Microsoft

Microsoft Certificate System Associate - MCSA

SQL Database Administrator- DBA

2015 - Microsoft

SharePoint Administration – Intranet and Portal (Configure and Administrating MS SharePoint)

2014 - ISO 27001:2013

Lead Implementer – Information Security Management System

BSI - British Standard Institute - Bahrain eGovernment

2012 - VMware

VMware vSphere: Install, Configure, Manage V5

Knowledge Village - Dubai, United Arab Emirates

2012 - Arab Open University

BSc in Business Administration

2011 - Microsoft

MCITP Server Administrator

CIO - Bahrain

2008 - Cisco

Cisco Certified Network Associate

Cisco - United State

2008 - Leaders

Information Technology Infrastructure Library (ITILv3)

EXIN - United State

2007 - The Leadership Trust (UK)

Leadership In Management Program

2006 - IIR (UAE)

Business Intelligent

2006 - Foundry Networks

- Core and edge switches
- Applications load balancer

2003 - Creative Knowledge

Future IT

2002 - BIBF

- Everything You Need to Know About Supervision
- Leadership Skills
- Communicating With Confidence

2002 - GBM (IBM)

- An Introduction to the Z/OS and OS/390 Environment
- Fundamental System Skills in Z/OS and OS/390
- Z/OS and OS/390 system Operations
- Z/OS and OS/390 J.C.L and utilities

2001 - New Horizon

- MCSE (Microsoft Certified System Engineering)
- MCP (Microsoft Certified Professional)

2001 - New Horizon

A+ Plus Certificate in Software and Hardware

COMPTIA - United State

1999 - ALBA

Training Technician (Instrumentation Department)

1999 - Bahrain Training Institute

National Diploma in Instrumentation and Process Control Engineering - BTEC - UK

Skills

- IT Solution Architecture (Hardware and Software)
- Cloud Administration (Amazon AWS and Microsoft Azure/ Microsoft 365)
- Servers and Desktop OS (DOS, Unix, Linux Distributions- Ubuntu, MAC OS and Windows)
- Mainframe (OS administration, connectivity and host integration system)
- Microsoft Servers (Hyper-V virtualization, Group policy, KPI certificates, Domain controllers, Domain names, DHCP, VPNs, IIS, FTP, Print services, Share folders, WSUS Patching system, Virtual Desktops, IAS and ADFS)
- Microsoft Systems (Office365, Exchange, Dynamics CRM, SharePoint, SQL DBA, PowerBI)
- Cisco (Routers, Firewall, Access points, Switches, UCS (blades and servers), IP phones (UC voice and video), IronPort email filtering)
- VMware (Server virtualization, Desktop virtualization, Application virtualization, VCloudAir with failover and back, NSX virtual network)
- Storage systems (EMC and NetApp)
- Firewalls (Fortinet, Untangle and Cyberoam)
- Wireless (Ruckus, Dragonwave, Ubiquiti and Foundery AP + Switches)
- Proxy and Caching engine (Blue Coat and Foundry Load Balancer)
- Antispam and Antivirus Systems (Kaspersky, Symantec and Ironmail)
- Backup Systems and Monitoring (Veeam, Veritas and CA BrightStor) with Automated Tape Library (HP, Dell and IBM)
- Helpdesk and Monitoring System (ManageEngine, PRTG Paessler)
- Programming in old Languages such as Clipper, dbase, Access, Visual Basic
- Others (Wireshark network troubleshoot and auditing, 802.1x network authentication implementation, pdq deploy Application deployment, Acronis OS image deployment, Video streaming, CCTV, Satellites, security systems and Access control systems)

Languages

English and Arabic

Interest

Technology Research and Sports